import { createContext, useContext, useEffect, useReducer } from "react";

const QuizContext = createContext();

const quizData = {
  "questions": [
    {
      "question": "Which is the most popular JavaScript framework?",
      "options": ["Angular", "React", "Svelte", "Vue"],
      "correctOption": 1,
      "points": 10
    },
    {
      "question": "Which company invented React?",
      "options": ["Google", "Apple", "Netflix", "Facebook"],
      "correctOption": 3,
      "points": 10
    },
    {
      "question": "What's the fundamental building block of React apps?",
      "options": ["Components", "Blocks", "Elements", "Effects"],
      "correctOption": 0,
      "points": 10
    },
    {
      "question": "What's the name of the syntax we use to describe the UI in React components?",
      "options": ["FBJ", "Babel", "JSX", "ES2015"],
      "correctOption": 2,
      "points": 10
    },
    {
      "question": "How does data flow naturally in React apps?",
      "options": [
        "From parents to children",
        "From children to parents",
        "Both ways",
        "The developers decides"
      ],
      "correctOption": 0,
      "points": 10
    },
    {
      "question": "How to pass data into a child component?",
      "options": ["State", "Props", "PropTypes", "Parameters"],
      "correctOption": 1,
      "points": 10
    },
    {
      "question": "When to use derived state?",
      "options": [
        "Whenever the state should not trigger a re-render",
        "Whenever the state can be synchronized with an effect",
        "Whenever the state should be accessible to all components",
        "Whenever the state can be computed from another state variable"
      ],
      "correctOption": 3,
      "points": 30
    },
    {
      "question": "What triggers a UI re-render in React?",
      "options": [
        "Running an effect",
        "Passing props",
        "Updating state",
        "Adding event listeners to DOM elements"
      ],
      "correctOption": 2,
      "points": 20
    },
    {
      "question": "When do we directly \"touch\" the DOM in React?",
      "options": [
        "When we need to listen to an event",
        "When we need to change the UI",
        "When we need to add styles",
        "Almost never"
      ],
      "correctOption": 3,
      "points": 20
    },
    {
      "question": "In what situation do we use a callback to update state?",
      "options": [
        "When updating the state will be slow",
        "When the updated state is very data-intensive",
        "When the state update should happen faster",
        "When the new state depends on the previous state"
      ],
      "correctOption": 3,
      "points": 30
    },
    {
      "question": "If we pass a function to useState, when will that function be called?",
      "options": [
        "On each re-render",
        "Each time we update the state",
        "Only on the initial render",
        "The first time we update the state"
      ],
      "correctOption": 2,
      "points": 30
    },
    {
      "question": "Which hook to use for an API request on the component's initial render?",
      "options": ["useState", "useEffect", "useRef", "useReducer"],
      "correctOption": 1,
      "points": 10
    },
    {
      "question": "Which variables should go into the useEffect dependency array?",
      "options": [
        "Usually none",
        "All our state variables",
        "All state and props referenced in the effect",
        "All variables needed for clean up"
      ],
      "correctOption": 2,
      "points": 30
    },
    {
      "question": "An effect will always run on the initial render.",
      "options": [
        "True",
        "It depends on the dependency array",
        "False",
        "In depends on the code in the effect"
      ],
      "correctOption": 0,
      "points": 30
    },
    {
      "question": "When will an effect run if it doesn't have a dependency array?",
      "options": [
        "Only when the component mounts",
        "Only when the component unmounts",
        "The first time the component re-renders",
        "Each time the component is re-rendered"
      ],
      "correctOption": 3,
      "points": 20
    }
  ]
}


const initialState = {
  questions: [],
  //"loading", "error" , "ready" , "active" , "finished"
  status: "loading",
  index: 0,
  answer: null,
  points: 0,
};
const reducer = (state, action) => {
  switch (action.type) {
    case "dataReceived":
      return { ...state, questions: action.payload, status: "ready" };
    case "dataFailed":
      return { ...state, status: "error" };
    case "start":
      return { ...state, status: "active" };
    case "newAnswer":
      const question = state.questions[state.index];
      return {
        ...state,
        answer: action.payload,
        points:
          action.payload === question.correctOption
            ? state.points + question.points
            : state.points,
      };
    case "nextQuestion":
      return {
        ...state,
        index: state.index + 1,
        answer: null,
        status:
          state.index + 1 === state.questions.length ? "finished" : "active",
      };
    case "finish":
      return { ...state, status: "finished" };
    case "reset":
      return { ...initialState, questions: state.questions, status: "ready" };
    default:
      throw new Error("Action unknown");
  }
};

function QuizProvider({ children }) {
  const [state, dispatch] = useReducer(reducer, initialState);
  const { questions, status, index, answer, points } = state;

  const numQuestions = questions.length;
  const maxPoints = questions.reduce((acc, curr) => acc + curr.points, 0);

  useEffect(() => {
    const data = JSON.parse(JSON.stringify(quizData.questions))
      dispatch({ type: "dataReceived", payload: data })
      
  }, []);

  return (
    <QuizContext.Provider
      value={{
        questions,
        index,
        status,
        answer,
        points,
        dispatch,
        numQuestions,
        maxPoints,
      }}
    >
      {children}
    </QuizContext.Provider>
  );
}

function useQuiz() {
  const context = useContext(QuizContext);
  if (context === undefined) {
    throw new Error("useQuiz must be used within an AuthProvider");
  }
  return context;
}

export { QuizProvider, useQuiz };
